Inventory of the Reed Family Papers, 1899-1946
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Reed Family Papers 1899-1946
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
2010.055
.66 Cubic Feet
Reed Family; Reed, Asa Daniel (circa 1888-unknown); Reed, Clarence Elizabeth; Reed, Eugene Mangus (November 28, 1923-unknown)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased in January 2010.
Biographical Information
Asa Daniel Reed, the son of P.A. Reed and Susan C. Reed, was born in Floyd County, Virginia, ca. 1888. He grew up in a farming family and served as a farm laborer until joining the U.S. Army on August 27, 1913, at the age of 24. Reed served in the ambulance and sanitary corps and rose to the rank of sergeant. His assignments included posts at the Regan Barracks in the Phillipines; Fort Clark, Texas; Fort Bliss, Texas; Fort D.A. Russel, Wyoming; Adernach, Germany; Verdun, France; and Camp Pike, Arkansas. Reed married his long term love interest, Clarence Elizabeth Mangus, in April 1920. He received an honorable discharge from the U.S. Army on June 4, 1920. Reed and his wife then moved to Warren, Ohio, where he began a career with the U.S. Postal Service. Reed's son, Eugene Mangus Reed, was born on November 28, 1923.
Clarence Elizabeth Reed was born as Clarence Elizabeth Mangus to H.J. Mangus and Kitty A. Mangus, farmers from Floyd County, Virginia. Clarence lived in Floyd County, Virgina before marrying Asa Daniel Reed and moving to Warren, Ohio in 1920. She gave birth to a son, Eugene Mangus Reed, on November 28, 1923.
Eugene Mangus Reed was born on November 28, 1923, in Warren, Ohio to Asa Daniel Reed and Clarence Elizabeth Reed. He served in the U.S. Army during World War II.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the papers and biographic material, 1899-1946, of the Reed family of Floyd County, Virgina and Warren, Ohio. Included are personal letters and photographs, as well as records relating to service of family members in WWI and WWII. The correspondence series consists largely of personal letters written by Asa Daniel Reed to his future wife, Clarence Elizabeth Mangus (later Clarence Elizabeth Reed), during Reed's service in the U.S. Army. Reed's assignments included posts in the Philippines during the U.S. occupation thereof, in Texas along the border with Mexico, and in Germany and France during World War I. Interwar correspondences focus more on Clarence Reed's domestic life in Warren, Ohio. During the World War II period, Asa and Clarence Reed received correspondences from their son, Eugene Mangus Reed, serving in the U.S. Army. The biographic material series includes publications from the late nineteenth century on health remedies, as well as brief histories of the Ohio and Erie Railroads. The series also contains Asa D. Reed's discharge papers from the U.S. Army, the baby book of Eugene Mangus Reed, and a photograph of Clarence Mangus.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: Series 1: Correspondence, Series 2: Biographic Material. Each series is arranged chronologically.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Philippines--Description and travel; World War, 1914-1918--France; World War, 1914-1918--United States.; World War, 1939-1945
Genre and Form Terms:
Correspondence; Photographs; Postcards
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series 1: Correspondence 1910-1946
  This series consists largely of personal letters written by Asa Daniel Reed to Clarence Elizabeth Mangus (later Clarence Elizabeth Reed) during Reed's service in the U.S. Army. From 1913 through 1920, Reed wrote to Mangus on a consistent basis from Army posts in Alabama, Georgia, the Philippines, Texas, Wyoming, Germany, France and Arkansas. During this time period Mangus resided in Floyd County, Virgina with her parents. Reed describes his military service in these letters, but focuses more so on his desire to return to civilian life and marry Mangus. Reed frequently refers to himself as "John" and to Mangus as "Irene." After their marriage in 1920, Asa and Clarence Reed moved to Warren, Ohio. Later items in this series include letters to Clarence Reed from her mother, Kitty A. Mangus, in Floyd County, Virgina. Clarence Reed also received frequent letters from a relative named Lila. During World War II, Asa and Clarence Reed received postcards and letters from their son, Eugene Mangus Reed, who also served in the U.S. Army. Other items in the collection include telegrams informing Asa Reed of family deaths, postcards from the World I and World War II era, and invitations to family weddings and school graduations.
  Chronological
  - Correspondence 1910-1912 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Correspondence 1913-1914 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Correspondence 1915 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Correspondence January-July 1916 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Correspondence August-December 1916 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Correspondence January-April 1917 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Correspondence May-July 1917 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Correspondence August-December 1917 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Correspondence 1918 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Correspondence January-June 1919 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Correspondence July-December 1919 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Correspondence 1920-1925 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Correspondence 1933-1938 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Correspondence 1940-1942 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Correspondence 1944 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Correspondence undated (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Correspondence undated (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Correspondence undated (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Correspondence undated (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Correspondence undated (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Telegrams 1921, 1925, 1928 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Postcards 1914, 1921, 1941-1944 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Invitations 1917-1946 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Greeting Cards 1925-1940 (Box-folder 2:12)
- Series 2: Biographic Material circa 1899-1942
  Items in this series include publications such as account books and pamphlets on health remedies. The series also contains Asa D. Reed's honorable discharge papers from the U.S. Army, which provides a brief summary of his service from August 27, 1913 through June 4, 1920. A baby book provides information on the birth and early years of Eugene Mangus Reed, the son of Asa and Clarence Reed. Other items of interest include advertisements for coffee companies and a local bank in Warren, Ohio. The series also contains a pamphlet for a sanitary train that Asa Reed served on in the military, as well as pamphlets on the Erie and Ohio railroads. The series concludes with one photograph of Clarence Mangus (Reed) and several unidentified photographs of what appear to be WWI German military officers.
  - Publications 1899, 1901 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Military Material 1920 (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Baby Books 1923 (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Advertisements 1931 (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Railroad Materials 1942 (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Photographs undated (Box-folder 2:18)